Roy Emrick papers, 1974-1984
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Roy Emrick papers, 1974-1984
MS 366
Emrick, Roy
Collection contains political, organizational and research materials pertaining to Dr. Emrick's involvement on several local and regional environmental organizations and water boards
3.5 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Dr. Roy Emrick serves on the faculty of the Department of Physics at the University of Arizona. He earned a B.S. in Physics from Cornell University and a PhD in Physics from the University of Illinois. In 1997 he received the College of Science Career Distinguished Teaching Award in recognition for his contributions to teaching. Dr. Emrick was actively involved in environmental and water conservations issues in Arizona. He was a member of the Arizona Sonora Desert Museum and the Sierra Club. He served on the Arizona Environmental Education Advisory Council. He was a member and eventually the chairman for Arizonans for Water Without Waste, and he was elected to serve as a representative to the Central Arizona Water Conservation District (1977-1984). Finally, he was active on the Committee on Alignment, Terminus and Storage, a committee of the organization Southern Arizona Water Resources Association The Arizona Environmental Education Advisory Council was established in 1967 as a volunteer organization. It served as an advisory board, counseling the Arizona Department of Education on issues of environmental education in public schools. Representatives were appointed by the State Superintendent of Public Instruction. Dr. Emrick was appointed to serve from March 1973 to July 1974. Arizonans for Water Without Waste (also known as Arizonans for Quality Environment) was created in 1967 by Arizonans concerned about the damming of the Grand Canyon. Eventually the scope of the group's environmental concerns expanded to include water, air quality, and wilderness and wildlife issues. The major annual project of the AWWW involved interviewing political candidates at all levels of government to determine the candidates' level of environmental awareness and support. The AWWW rated and endorsed candidates according to their environmental stances. Dr. Emrick served as the last chairman of AWWW in 1983. The Central Arizona Water Conservation District is a state agency created in 1971 by the Arizona State Legislature with representation from Pima, Pinal and Maricopa Counties. Representatives are elected from each county based on county population. The CAWCD is responsible for repayment of reimbursable construction costs of the Central Arizona Project to the federal government. Eventually the CAWCD was designated by the Legislature as the agency to manage the Project. As such CAWCD is concerned with water fees and property taxes for CAP, water allocation, canal operation and maintenance. The District works closely with various interest groups including Native American Tribes, the State Governor, the Arizona Power Authority, the Bureau of Reclamation, the Department of the Interior and the State Congressional Delegation. Dr. Emrick served as a representative from Pima County for two four-year terms from 1977 through 1984. Southern Arizona Water Resources Association represents the interests and ideas of local individuals to assure stable, long-term, high quality water supplies and effective management for the Tucson basin. SAWRA does this by promoting education, outreach and coalition building. Dr. Emrick served on the Committee on Alignment, Terminus and Storage (CATS), which was specifically concerned with the Tucson Aqueduct, Phase B. The group was opposed to the creation of a reservoir at the base of Cat Mountain southeast of Tucson.
Organization
This collection is organized into seven series:
Series I: Arizona Environmental Education Advisory Council, 1973-1974
Series II: Arizonans for Water Without Waste (AWWW), 1970-1983
Series III: Central Arizona Water Conservation District, 1976-1984
Series IV: Maps, 1982
Series V: Publications, 1978-1984
Series VI: Reports, 1973-1984
Series VII: Southern Arizona Water Resources Association, 1982-1983
Scope and Content Note
Series One, "Arizona Environmental Education Advisory Council," (1973-1974) contains Dr. Emrick's letter of appointment from Superintendent W. P. Shofstall, administrative papers of the AEEAC and meeting minutes from council meetings. Series Two, "Arizonans for Water Without Waste," (1970-1983) contains administrative records including organizational correspondence, AWWW Newsletters, meeting minutes, press releases and public statements. The bulk of this series is candidate interviews on environmental issues. Interviews are of candidates from local city council and mayoral races, county board of supervisor's races, state legislative races, gubernatorial races, state attorney's general races and U.S. congressional races. These papers include candidates' personal responses on AWWW questionnaires and notes taken by AWWW members during candidate interviews. Papers also include AWWW candidate ratings and endorsements. Series Three, "Central Arizona Water Conservation District" (1976-1984), contains administrative papers for the District. These papers are not necessarily organizational in nature, but rather reflect Dr. Emrick's personal involvement with the CAWCD. Therefore the bulk of the material in this series is contained in the Meeting files. These papers include meeting agendas and minutes, financial and budgetary reports, personnel policies and issues, legal and contractual papers, and administrative and legislative papers. Also included are reports, correspondence and other works, which provide background information for the subjects of discussion at the board meetings. As meeting minutes were approved at the subsequent board meeting, minutes are included with the file for the subsequent meeting. Meeting files are arranged by meeting date. Additionally, this series includes campaign materials from Dr. Emrick's campaign and election in 1976, organizational correspondence, newspaper clippings, personal notes, litigation records, federal and state contracts, scientific studies and reports, papers pertaining to the Tucson Division of CAP, the Parker-Davis Repayment Program, the Orme Dam Alternatives Task Force and the Papago Indian Water Rights Settlement. Series Four, "Maps" (1982) includes several maps outlining the various proposals under consideration for Phase B of the Tucson Aqueduct. Series Five, "Publications" (1978-1984) contains regular publications from various watch groups and organizations including the Department of the Interior, the Bureau of Reclamation, the Tucson Division, The Central Arizona Project Association, and Western Resources Roundup. (Some copies of these publications are included the CAWCD Meeting files). Series Six, "Reports" (1973-1984) contains various scientific studies and reports prepared to study the Central Arizona Project, its impacts and wider implications. Some were prepared by private individuals and others by organizations including the Department of the Interior, the Bureau of Reclamation, the Arizona Water Commission and the Arizona Power Authority. Series Seven, " Southern Arizona Water Resources Association" (1982-1983) contains newspaper clippings pertaining to the proposed Cat Mountain Reservoir and Phase B of the Tucson Aqueduct, organizational correspondence and meeting minutes.
Arizonans for Water Without Waste; Arizona Environmental Education Advisory Council; Southern Arizona Water Resources Association; Central Arizona Project (U.S.); Water conservation -- Arizona; Water-supply -- Arizona -- Tucson Region; Water consumption -- Arizona; Water districts -- Arizona; Water reuse -- Arizona; Water resources development -- Arizona; Water conservation -- Citizen participation; Central Arizona Water Conservation District; Orme Dam (Ariz.); Tucson Aqueduct (Ariz.); Tucson (Ariz.) -- History
Container List
- Series 1: Arizona Environmental Education Advisory Council, 1973-1974
  - Arizona Environmental Education Advisory Council, March 7, 1973- March, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Arizonans for Water Without Waste, 1970-1983
  - AWWW: Administration, October 22, 1970-October 2, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - AWWW: Correspondence (Incoming), May 5, 1972-August 30, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AWWW: Correspondence (Outgoing), May 22, 1970-July 22, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Tucson City Council Elections, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Tucson Mayoral and City Council Elections, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Pima County Board of Supervisors Election, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Tucson City Council Elections, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Arizona State Legislature Elections, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Tucson City Council Elections, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Pima County Board of Supervisors Election, U.S. Congressional Elections (1 of 2), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Arizona State Legislature Elections (2 of 2), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - U.S. Congressional Elections, Arizona Gubernatorial Elections, Arizona Attorney General Election, Arizona Corporate Commission Election (1 of 4), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Arizona State Legislature Elections, Candidates A-E (2 of 4), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Arizona State Legislature Elections, Candidates F-K (3 of 4), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Arizona State Legislature Elections, Candidates L-R (4 of 4), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - AWWW: Candidate Interviews - Tucson Mayoral and City Council Elections, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - AWWW: Newsletters, August 1976-November 1982 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - AWWW: Minutes of Meetings, February 26, 1973-February 14, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - AWWW: Newspaper Clippings 1973-1983 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - AWWW: Press Releases and Public Statements September 4, 1973-August 24, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1974-1984 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Series III: Central Arizona Water Conservation District, 1976-1984
  - CAWCD: Administration, February 7, 1977-July 13, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - CAWCD: Campaign Materials, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - CAWCD: CAP/Dam Boondogles, August 29, 1977-August 25, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - CAWCD: Central Arizona Project Master Contract, December 15, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - CAWCD: Colorado River Comprehensive Environmental Impact Statement, September 14, 1977-December 7, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - CAWCD: Correspondence (Incoming) December, 1977-November, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - CAWCD: Correspondence (Internal), November 16, 1977-October 25, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - CAWCD: Groundwater Commission October, 1977-November 3, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - CAWCD: Litigation - Gila River Indian Community vs. CAWCD et. al., January 4, 1977-March 11, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - CAWCD: Litigation - Irrigation District Resolutions, March 16, 1977-March 22, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - CAWCD: Litigation - Validation of the CAP Master Contract, June 18, 1977-August 12, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, December 16, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, January 3, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, March 3, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, April 7, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, June 2, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, September 8, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, November 3, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, December 1, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, March 17, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, June 1, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, September 14, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, January 18, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, May 3, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, July 19, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, October 4, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, November 1, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, January 24, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, April 29, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, June 5, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, November 6, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, January 8, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, March 5, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, 1974/1984 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, July 10, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, (Information Session) (1 of 2) September 18 & 19, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors (Information Session) (2 of 2), September 18 & 19, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, October 5, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, January 7, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, February 9, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, March 4, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, April 12, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, May 6, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors. June 17, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, September 2, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, October 7, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, November 4, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, December 2, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, January 6, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors (Information Session), March 4 & 5, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, March 5, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors (Joint meeting with the Arizona Power Authority), March 28, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, May 12, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, July 7, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, September 1, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, November 3, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, December 1, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, January 5, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors (Information Session), March 1 & 2, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, March 2, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, May 3, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, July 5, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, September 6, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, October 4, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - CAWCD: Meeting - Board of Directors, December 6, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - CAWCD: Newspaper Clippings, March 12, 1977-December 18, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - CAWCD: Orme Dam Alternatives, October 25, 1977-October 12, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - CAWCD: Orme Dam Alternatives Interagency Task Force Final Report, May 5, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - CAWCD: Papago Indian Water Rights Settlement, August 3, 1981-September 22, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - CAWCD: Parker-Davis Repayment, June 15, 1977-March 17, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - CAWCD: Tucson Aqueduct Phase B, November 1981-April 22, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - CAWCD: Tucson Division Central Arizona Project, March 28, 1978-May 8, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - CAWCD: The White House Statement on Water Projects, April 18, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Series IV: Maps, 1982
  - Maps 1982 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- Series V: Publications, 1978-1984
  - Publications: Department of the Interior News Releases, September 4, 1981-December 5, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Publications: Information Paper: Central Arizona Project, Bureau of Reclamation, October 1978-November 1979 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Publications: Re:CAP Central Arizona Project Tucson Division, November 1978-May 1983 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Publications: Watergram, Central Arizona Project Association, July 1981-March 1982 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Publications: Western Resources Roundup, June 11, 1981-December 13, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Publications: Miscellaneous Groups, May 1974-March 29, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Series VI: Reports, 1973-1984
  - Reports: Arizona Power Authority Legislation Enacted by Arizona Legislature, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Reports: Arizona Water Resources Management Act of 1977 by Robert Emmet Clark, University of Arizona, College of Law, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Reports: The Central Arizona Project by Howard A. Brown, Congressional Research Service, April 20, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reports: Central Arizona Project: An Independent Critique by Citizens Ad Hoc Committee on the Central Arizona Project, July 18, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Reports: Public Workshops Participants' Workbook, Central Arizona Water Control Study, April-May 1980 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reports: Public Forums Factbook, Central Arizona Water Control Study, November-December 1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reports: Summary Factbook, Central Arizona Water Control Study, October 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Reports: Hoover Power Marketing Public Information Forum, Arizona Power Authority, September 14, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Reports: Preliminary Central Arizona Project Alternatives for Eastern Pima County Regional Water Resources Study: CAP Tucson Division, U.S. Bureau of Reclamation Arizona Projects Office (Draft and Final Report), May 1979-August 1979 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Reports: Projected Water Uses, Supplies and Groundwater Conditions in Selected Basins in Arizona: A Baseline Conditions Report to the Groundwater Management Study Commission, Arizona Water Commission, April, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Reports: Water Policy Implementation Final Report on Phase I, Department of the Interior, June 6, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Series VII: Southern Arizona Water Resources Association, 1973-1984
  - SAWRA: Clippings (Cat Mountain), November 26, 1982-January 12, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - SAWRA: Correspondence (Incoming), October 29, 1982-May 13, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - SAWRA: Correspondence (Outgoing), April 29, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - SAWRA: Minutes of Meetings, September 24, 1982-February 2, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 15)